TheChaosLegion
l want to shine on you,
and always like that dazzling sun.
l will defend you
from all the darkness.
This is the truth from my heart.
lf only our hearts could connect,
l could get you to believe me.
Even if you can't
see it now, don't lose it.
Your kindness won't be in vain.
You'll be carried aloft by the wind
to somewhere that isn't here.
You'll cross the sea and cross time,
and l know you'll blossom one day.
Whatever the day,
l'll be there for you.
l hope l can watch over you
like the sun for all time.
This is the truth from my heart.
Moribito Guardian of the Spirit
～♪
Has it been two years?
（バルサ）２年ぶりか
Episode 1
Balsa,
the
Female
Bodyguard
（子供たち）♪ 鍬(くわ)入れろ
...and swing your plows!
Sow the rice seeds
and make the seedlings sprout!
Nahji, come, come!
Swarm like a black cloud and
fly down from the northern mountains.
ヨゴはいいな
気持ちが穏やかになる
lt's good to be in Yogo.
l can feel my soul
growing more tranquil.
何だい？
What is it?
lt's not often that you
see a woman warrior.
女の武人とは珍しい
カンバルから来たのかね？
Are you from Kanbal?
Well, yes. l'm here for
maintenance on my short spear.
まあね
短槍(たんそう)のメンテナンスを
してもらうのさ
メンテナンス？
Maintenance?
Well, unlike Kanbal, you can
get anything you need in Yogo.
ヨゴはカンバルと違って
何でも手に入る
That's assuming, of course,
that you have money.
もっとも 金があればの話だがね
（バルサ）かもな
Perhaps.
But those with money end up
living the same life wherever they go.
だが 金を持っていると―
どこに行っても
同じ生き方をしてしまう
Having none, however, means
you can live as those around you do.
けど 金がなければ
その場に合った生き方ができる
And there's really nothing
wrong with that.
それは それで 悪くない
ほう 若いのに面白いことを言う
You're quite philosophical
for someone so young.
もう若くないよ
l'm not young anymore.
l'll be 30 this year.
今年で30だ
おい！ あんた
Listen, you!
皇族の一行だ
lt's a royal family procession!
But l'm not from this country.
私は この国の人間じゃない
何の義理もないよ
l have no obligation whatsoever.
He's going to fall!
（行商人）落ちるぞ！
あれか
There he is...
（バルサ）子供？
He's just a child?
What happened back there?
何だい？ ありゃ
He must've lost
consciousness right away.
すぐに気を失ったんだね
水は飲んでいない
He didn't swallow any water.
（従者）のけい！
Step aside!
Commoners such as you must never
look upon one of the royal family!
お前ら下賤(げせん)の者が
皇族を見てはならん！
Do not look at him!
（従者）見るでない！
（従者）急ぎ かごと医者の手配を！
Do not look at him!
Hurry, send for a carriage and doctor!
Listen! Get rid of that crowd!
（従者）おい 早く人払いを
（トーヤ）やっぱりタンダか
l had a feeling it was you, Tanda.
ls something wrong?
どうしたんです？
扇(おうぎ)の下(しも)まで足をのばすなんて
For you to come all
the way to Ogi no Shimo...
l gather she hasn't come here yet?
（タンダ）
まだ あいつは来てないみたいだな
すんません
Sorry, Tanda.
But it's been two years now.
でも もう２年ですから
そろそろ バルサねえさん―
l wouldn't be surprised if Balsa
came back any day now.
帰ってきても
おかしくないころですよ
だと いいんだがな
l hope you're right...
（サヤ）
タンダさん 寄っていきませんか？
Would you like to come inside, Tanda?
いや また今度 寄らせてもらうよ
No, l'll visit with you some other time.
薬草の注文が入っていて―
l have an order for medicinal herbs,
so l'll be in town for a few days.
２～３日は
街で仕事をしているから
lf we hear anything about Balsa,
you'll be the first to know.
バルサねえさんの ウワサ入ったら
真っ先に知らせますんで
l hear they read this
would-be hero the riot act!
Can you believe the gall of that guy?
（女性）お待ちどおさま あいよ
Thank you for your patience.
Sake! Bring us some more sake!
Here you go!
Very well!
（役人）待たれよ！
１つ聞きたいことがある
Wait!
There is something
we'd like to ask you.
本日 青弓川(あおゆみがわ)にて 皇族の者を
救った武人がいたと聞き―
We heard that a warrior
rescued a member...
...of the royal family
from Aoyumi River today.
その者を捜しておる
We are searching for this person.
Rumor has it that this warrior
was a short-spear bearer.
ウワサでは
その者 短槍使いだったそうだ
Would you happen to know
anything of this warrior?
何か心当たりはござらぬか？
（バルサ）さあね
Not a thing...
Just as l thought.
（役人）だろうな
Forget we had this conversation!
（役人）今の話は忘れてくれ
忘れろって態度じゃないね
l can see you don't
want me to just forget it.
l wouldn't if l were you.
やめな！
お前の腕じゃ
刀を抜く前に２度死ぬよ
With your skills, you'd be killed twice
before your sword was drawn.
Wait!
（役人）待たれよ！
無礼を承知の行状じゃ
l realize we have
acted with disrespect.
我々は宮中(きゅうちゅう)からの使いで―
We are emissaries from the court...
二ノ妃(にのきさき)の命により
そなたを捜しておったのだ
...and have been searching for you
on orders of the second queen.
The second queen?
二ノ妃？
（役人）腕の立つ武人と聞き つい
男ばかりを尋ね歩いていたが―
Hearing that it was a skilled
warrior who saved the prince...
...we assumed it was a man,
and have only been questioning men.
たった今 そなたであると確信した
But l am now convinced
that this warrior was, in fact, you.
You have my word
that we will do you no harm!
決して悪いようには いたさん
Please, do us the honor of
accompanying us to Ninomiya Palace.
どうか 我々と共に
二ノ宮(にのみや)まで ご同行くだされ
Not what l had in mind.
まいったね…
こいつを
先に直しに行きゃ よかったよ
l should've had this repaired
as soon as l arrived.
Moribito Guardian of the Spirit
This is quite a view.
絶景だな フッ
ここで これほどとなると―
lf this palace is so lavish, the mikado's
lifestyle must be beyond belief.
帝(みかど)の暮らしってのは
想像を絶するもんなんだろうね
せっかくの ごちそうも
これじゃあね
l'd hate to see this feast go to waste.
今更 毒を盛る必要もないか
Then again, why would
they poison me now?
（侍従長）
わざわざ招いておきながら―
Forgive us for not being more
effusive after inviting you here.
このような もてなししか
できなくて申し訳ない
異邦人である そなたは
存じておらぬやも知れんが
A foreigner such as yourself
might not be aware of this, but...
We commoners are unable
to look directly into the eyes...
我々 下賤の者が 皇族と
じかに目を合わせることはできない
...of a member of the royal family.
lf we do, we will instantly
be struck blind in both eyes.
見れば たちまち
両の眼(まなこ)が つぶれてしまう
Well, that is one of the reasons...
ああ… まあ
そういった理由もあるが―
二ノ妃は
皇子を救ってくれたことに対し―
But the second queen is most
grateful to you for saving the prince.
心から感謝しておられる
This money is your reward.
これは報賞金だ
The amount is paltry for the life
of a prince, but please accept it.
皇子の命の代償としては
いささか少なくはあるが―
収めてくれ
それとな 二ノ妃より―
Also, Her Majesty the
second queen herself...
こよいは こちらで一晩
泊まってゆかれるようにと―
...has instructed me to ask you
to spend the night here.
じきじきに仰せつかっている
いえ ここまでしていただいて
もう十分
No, you have already done
more than enough for me.
Now, now...
なにとぞ泊まっていってくだされ
Please, do us the honor
of staying the night.
Your belongings have been
taken to your room.
（侍女）手荷物は 全て
部屋の中にございます
（バルサ）ありがとう
Thank you.
What can l say?
At any rate, what on earth
is this futon made of?
にしても何だい？ この布団
こんなものに 毎晩 寝てるから
雲上人なんて言われるのかね？
l wonder if the nobility are called
"those who dwell on the clouds"...
...because they sleep on
these huge things every night.
まあ いいか
Oh, never mind!
This may be my only chance to
experience what they call "heaven"!
生涯一度かもしれない
極楽気分ってやつを楽しむとするか
Warrior from another land...
（二ノ妃）
異国の武人よ 目覚めておろうか？
Are you awake?
Yes, l'm awake. Please come in.
（バルサ）起きております どうぞ
l see that you are indeed
as formidable a woman as they say.
（二ノ妃）
さすがは 強いというウワサの女人
You look us in the eye,
and yet you do not fall blind.
私たちの目を見ても
目がつぶれることはないようじゃ
今日は よくぞ
皇子を救ってくれました
Thank you for
rescuing the prince today.
You have my deepest gratitude.
心から感謝しています
（バルサ）もったいない お言葉
l am unworthy of your kind words.
すでに身に余る歓待を
受けております
You have already shown me
hospitality of the highest order.
Any further gestures
are most unnecessary.
これ以上のお心遣いは
もはや不要にございます
l see.
そうか
Even so, l expect that you
must find our coming to visit you...
だが そなた 何故 我らが
こんな夜更けに ここへ来たか―
...in the middle of the night
to be most unusual.
不思議に思っておるであろう
Look up, Balsa. Show me your face!
面を上げよ バルサ
従者たちが申していたとおりの
いい面構えじゃ
Just as my attendants said,
you have a fearless look in your eye.
通り名は“短槍使いのバルサ”
You are known by the name
Balsa the Spear-wielder.
その筋では
その名を知らぬ者はなく―
They say that there are none
who do not know your name...
...that you have the appearance
of a warrior of distant Kanbal...
姿は
遠きカンバルの武人に似ており―
その腕前で
何人もの命を救ってきたそうだな
...and that your skills have
saved many lives over the years.
ls this wrong?
違うか？
（バルサ）
恐れながら それは あまりに
キレイすぎるウワサごと
Your Majesty...
What you have heard are no more than
rumors that embellish my reputation.
私は金で雇われ他人を守る
一介の用心棒にございます
l am a bodyguard who protects
others for money, nothing more.
Ah, l see.
なるほど
Why do you risk your life
to earn money performing such work?
そなたは―
なぜ 命を懸けてまで
そのような仕事で金を稼ぐ？
ln truth, it is the hope
that l place in your ability...
実はな そなたの腕を見込んで
頼みたいことがあるのじゃ
...that has brought me
here to ask this favor.
どこへ逃げてもかまわぬ
l do not care where you flee.
これから先 この子を一生涯―
Will you take this child...
...and protect him for the rest of
his life from the mikado's assassins?
帝の刺客より
守り通してはくれぬか？
帝の刺客？
From the mikado's assassins?
Today it was an ox cart.
今日は 牛車(ぎっしゃ)が…
半月前にも 湯治場の湯が
突然 噴き出し―
Half a month ago,
he had a narrow escape...
危うく命を落としかけている
...when a geyser suddenly
erupted at the hot springs.
But why in the world would
the mikado want to kill the prince?
（バルサ）ですが
何故 皇子様のお命を？
lt all began some two months ago.
あれは２か月ほど前のこと…
Night after night, the child began
mumbling strange things in his sleep.
この子が夜な夜な 妙なことを
口走るようになったので―
カシヅキである星読み博士に
寝姿を見させたところ―
When l had his tutor, a star reader,
observe him as he slept...
何か得体(えたい)の知れぬものが―
...he told me that some unknown
force had possessed the child.
この子の体に
取りついていると申すのじゃ
Fortunately, this star reader
is honorable and trustworthy.
幸い その星読みは
信頼のおける好人物
We told no one, turning instead
to a magic weaver of the Yakoo.
このことを他言せず―
ヤクーの呪術師に
相談してみようということになった
However, the star reader consulted
not only this magic weaver...
だが その星読みは―
呪術師だけでなく 聖導師(せいどうし)にも
このことを相談していたのじゃ
...but the master star reader as well.
l suspect that the mikado
secretly ordered the prince's death...
恐らく帝は
聖導師からの進言を伝え聞き―
...upon receiving
the master star reader's counsel.
この子を ひそかに
亡き者にするよう命じたのであろう
それだけの理由で…
Merely for that reason?
（二ノ妃）もし このことが
ウワサとなって広まれば―
lf word of this gets out
and rumors begin to spread...
神の子である帝の威信を
なおしようもなく傷つけてしまう
...it would irreparably damage
the good name of the mikado.
You! Have you been
disrespectful to my mother?
（チャグム）お前！
母君に何か無礼を働いたのか？
No, she has not, Chagum.
（二ノ妃）違うのですよ チャグム
l have asked her to
safeguard your life.
私は あなたの命を救うよう―
この者に頼んでいたのです
待ってください！
But wait a moment...
Wait!
待って！
チャグム よく お聞き
Chagum, you must listen to me.
From this moment on, l want you
to follow her wherever she goes...
今から あなたは
この者についていき―
どんなことがあっても
死んではならない
...and no matter what happens,
you must not die.
帝が あなたを
亡き者とすると決めたときから―
You ceased to be a prince the instant
the mikado ordered your death.
あなたは皇子ではなくなったのです
（二ノ妃）
でも 帝を恨んではいけません
Even so, you must not harbor
ill will towards the mikado.
He bears the terrible responsibility
of ruling this country.
帝には この国を統べるという
大事な責任があるのです
あれを持て！
Bring it in.
A commoner could not spend all
this in a lifetime, try as she might.
下々の民草では
一生かかっても使い切れまい
Please give me your word that you
will accept this and protect my child.
どうか それで
この子を守ると約束しておくれ
（バルサ）お妃様
お話は 大体 分かりました
Your Majesty, l understand the gist
of your request. However...
ですが これは あまりにも
ひきょうな仕打ちでございます
This is a most dishonorable
way for you to treat me.
ln what way?
どういうことじゃ？
For my life to be forfeit as a reward
for having saved the prince's life...
皇子の命を救った褒美が
命を奪われることでは―
ひきょうとも言いたくなる
How is that not dishonorable?
No one is suggesting
that you be killed.
誰もそなたの命を奪うなどとは
申しておらぬ
そうでしょうか？
Are you certain about that?
私のような身分の者が
こんな話を聞かされたら―
lf someone of my low social status
were to hear a story such as yours...
...that person would have no choice
but to agree to your request.
お妃様の願いを聞く以外に
選ぶ道はない
And yet once she agreed, her life
would be more or less in jeopardy.
ですが 聞き入れたところで
命の保障もない
And you are too unfamiliar with
the ways of the world, Your Majesty.
しかも お妃様は
度を超した世間知らず
宮の紋章が入った宝石など使えば
たちまち足がついてしまいます
lf l ever tried to pay for something
with gems bearing this palace crest...
...our whereabouts would be
discovered at once.
そうか…
l see. However, this is the only money
that l have at my disposal.
けれど 私の自由になるお金は
それしかないのじゃ
確かに この秘密を知った者を―
But you are correct.
l cannot allow one who has...
ただで
生かしておくわけにはいかんな
...learned this secret to leave
without consequence.
Balsa! You can either die here or take
a chance at survival with the prince.
バルサよ
今 ここで死ぬか
皇子と生き抜く希望に懸けるか―
どちらかを選べ！
Choose one or the other!
お妃様といえど
心を許せる手勢は少ないようですね
For a queen...
...you certainly don't seem to
have many trustworthy men.
Two in the room behind me.
Three in the hallway.
後ろの部屋に２名 廊下に３名
Counting these two, you have
seven in all, which is quite pitiful.
この者たちを入れて７名とは哀れだ
Don't make a move!
動くんじゃないよ！
For starters, l'll take the treasure.
では まず宝を頂きましょうか
そら！
You two!
それに入るだけ入れな
Fill this with as much as will fit!
お妃様
Your Majesty, earlier you asked
why it is that l work as a bodyguard.
先ほど なぜ私が 用心棒を
しているのかと聞かれましたね
私は ある事情から―
ln the past, l was forced to take
the lives of eight dear people.
８人の大切な人の命を
奪ってしまった過去がある
And so, to appease the souls
of those eight people...
ですから
その８人の魂を弔うべく―
それと対等の命を救うまで
用心棒稼業を続けているのです
...l am working as a bodyguard until
l've saved an equal number of lives.
８人の魂…
Eight people's souls?
皇子を引き受けましょう
l will protect the prince.
行くのじゃチャグム
お前も この者を信じて
Go with her, Chagum.
Trust her as l do.
さあ
Come!
（二ノ妃）あっ…
（チャグム）母君！
Mother!
No, l don't want to go! Mother!
嫌じゃ！ 母君！
そこの者
皇子を無事 逃がしたければ―
You! lf you want the prince
to escape to safety...
まず皇子の寝間に火をかけろ
...start by setting a fire
in his bedchamber!
そして私たちを
逃げ道まで案内するんだ
And then take us to the
palace's secret escape route!
およこし！
Hand me the bag.
Take care, Your Majesty.
では お妃様 お達者で
Balsa!
バルサよ！
わが息子の命
そなたが救う何番目の命じゃ？
lf you include my son's life,
how many lives will you have saved?
８人目の命にございます
Your Majesty, his life will be the eighth.
As l sat huddled and alone, holding
back the tears on those nights...
When it felt like l was about
to succumb to my doubts...
...there you were,
at my side before l knew it.
lt was none other than you
who was there for me.
l keep wishing, "l want to be strong."
l stumble and hurt myself again.
But because l have you to believe in,
l can get back to my feet.
l simply want to tell
my dear one, "Thank you."
At the top of my lungs,
again and again.
l call out to my precious loved one.
ls my voice reaching you?
ln this world that always changes,
human warmth never does.
l'm certain l sensed the presence
of the one that l hold dear.
～♪
Next Time
Balsa goes into hiding in the Yogo city.
But she and Chagum
are given no time to rest.
Next time, "Hunters, Hunted."
Episode 2
Hunters, Hunted
The mikado's shadow servants...
...are about to be unleashed.